Today
is י"ג *Yud Gimmel*, is second פרק *Perek*, כל היד *Kol Hayad*,
top of י"ג עמוד א' *Yud Gimmel Amud Alef*. And here we
go. So we've been talking all of last פרק *Perek* about, we
start with when a woman finds blood, how much backwards does she
have to be concerned that she might have been bleeding? And then
it got us into the practice of women who regularly check at
least at a time when they were עוסקות בטהרות *oskos b'taharos*, when
they were dealing with טהרות *taharos*, twice a day, once in the
morning, once in the evening, and before and after sex. And now
this פרק *Perek* opens with a very general statement. So let's take
a look. כל היד המרבה לבדוק בנשים משובחת ובאנשים תקצץ *Kol hayad
hamarbeh livdok b'nashim meshubachas, uv'anashim tikatzeitz*. Okay,
very clear, apodictic, powerful statement. Any, all hands that are that have
sort of like כל המרבה לספר ביציאת מצרים הרי זה משובח *kol
hamarbeh lesaper b'yitziat mitzrayim harei zeh meshubach*. You see the exact parallel:
כל המרבה משובחת *kol hamarbeh meshubachas*, whoever does more is praised. So
כל היד המרבה לבדוק בנשים משובחת *kol hayad hamarbeh livdok b'nashim meshubachas*.
Every hand that checks more frequently amongst women should be praised. The
more a woman checks, the better. That's in contrast, by the way,
to שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel* says nowadays when you don't have a טהרה
*taharah* concern, he actually says that checking before and after sex is
forbidden because it creates greater anxiety. But at least in the context
of these משניות *mishnayos*, the more you check, the better. That's for
women. But for men, ובאנשים תקצץ *uv'anashim tikatzeitz*, it should be cut
off. Presumably that's a little bit of an exaggeration, but obviously means
it's a very bad thing. Don't check for men anymore than is
strictly necessary. So the reason seems clear or whatever once you know
the general concerns of the גמרא Gemara? *Gemara*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
will make it explicit. It's not explicit in the משנה mishna *Mishnah*.
So let's just go right into the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. מאי שנא
נשים ומאי שנא אנשים anashim, *Mai shena nashim u-mai shena anashim*? Why
are women different than men? נשים לאו בנות הרגשה benot hargasha נינהו
*Nashim lav bnot hargasha ninhu*. Women are, I'm going to translate this
and then I will discuss it. So women are not daughters,
do not have sensation or are not בנות הרגשה hargasha *bnot hargasha*.
So
therefore משובחת *meshubachas*, they are to be praised the more they check.
אנשים דבני הרגשה hargasha נינהו *Anashim debnei hargasha ninhu*, that they are
children of sensation, they have sensation. תקצץ *Tikatzeitz*, it should be cut
off. Now what does this mean? Clearly as we're going to see
in a minute, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has a very major concern
with שכבת זרע לבטלה zera l'vattala. *shichvat zera levatala*, with ejaculation of
semen not in the context of marital sex. And therefore masturbation. But
masturbation leading to ejaculation, although it's interesting and I'll discuss as we
learn the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*, is there concern of masturbation per se
even independent of ejaculation? But certainly that's a concern. So it says
that's a concern for men, it's not a concern for women. Now
why is it not a concern for women? So here the way
it frames it is women are not בנות הרגשה *bnot hargasha*. What
does this mean? Look at רש"י Rashi *Rashi*. רש"י *Rashi* says הרגשה
*hargasha*, first fair line, שמזדעזעין איבריו כשמתחמם ורואה קרי *she-mizdazin avarav keshe-mis-chamem
v'ro-eh keri*.
Men, their limbs, but probably also means specifically their genitals, get, but
their whole body maybe, gets excited, sexually excited, or sort of tremble
when they get heated up, when they get sexually excited. And that
leads to ejaculation. אנשים משובח *Anashim meshubach*, okay. Now why is that
not true by women? So he doesn't say explicitly, but presumably the
point is, let me just
check one minute. Hold on.
No, okay, so he doesn't say what is not the case by
women. He doesn't explicitly say what the context is by women. But
it seems to be the point is that women don't have seminal
emissions. They don't have a reality called זרע לבטלה zera l'vattala. *zera
levatala*. Now we will talk about it in a minute because I'll
talk to you about תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* who is concerned. And there
are גמרות Gemaros. *Gemaros* that actually acknowledge a reality by women called
that women are מזרע *mazria*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* actually acknowledged that
women have orgasm and that leads to liquids
being released by the body in the through the vagina. And the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* actually does sometimes refer to the reality of women
being what it calls מזרע *mazria*. Actually, interestingly,
in the ancient period until about I think 200 years ago, or
maybe less, there was this the idea of how conception occurs was
this was this concept of anyway was the sort of two-seed theory,
which is that you require the seed of the man and the
seed of the woman. And there are actually a number of גמרות
*Gemaros* that refer to the idea like the famous
רש"י *Rashi* quoting the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, אשה כי תזריע *isha ki
tazria*, when a woman is
מזרע *mazria* gives forth seed and gives birth to a
male, רש"י *Rashi* says אשה מזרעת תחילה יולדת זכר *isha mazria techila
yoledet zachar*. ...because that actually put at the center of the concern
female orgasm and that actually comes up in a number of גמרות
*Gemaras* because you can't have conception without that. And the גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara* actually talks about the man being making sure that the husband
making sure that his wife has orgasm and is מזריעה *mazria* and
מזריעה תחילה *mazria techila* and all those types of issues. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is certainly, what? You don't have to check. You
can't have a male, right? But actually interestingly, okay, clearly there was
a bias towards men, there's no question about that, but it's quite
interesting how that bias actually fed into ensuring female or promoting female
satisfaction during marital sex because of the emphasis therefore of אשה מזריעה
תחילה *Isha mazria techila*. And in general that is a concern in
the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* finds... and it was
not just גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, it was generally in the ancient world
the conception, the understanding of how babies were conceived. Actually there's a
book written about this that I read, I'm sure there's more than
one book, that once they discovered that really female orgasm was not
at all necessary biologically for conception, it led to a complete disregard
by men for the value of female orgasm. So that is one
thing to acknowledge, though wait a minute, that the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*
does have a concept of אשה מזריעה *Isha mazria*. Nevertheless, why it's
not concerned here with women checking themselves and the potential of sort
of sexual stimulation and arousal, it could be read in one of
two ways. It could be read, even before we get to תוספות
Tosafos *Tosafot*, but within רש"י *Rashi*, either that it believes that that
type of
stimulation, physical stimulation of the pubic area of the genital area did
not lead to orgasm by women,
which is not true, maybe it's not as immediate as it is
by men, but maybe it was but nevertheless it wasn't sustained. Maybe
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* was not concerned that the result would be
as immediate. That's one way, which is most literal in terms of
the frame of הרגשה *hargasha*. We're not concerned that the time it
takes you to check if you're bleeding or whatever for women is
going to have that type of an arousal effect as it does
by men. The other possibility, which is
and I think this is made more explicit in the הרא"ש *ha-Rosh*
that discusses רש"י *Rashi*, is it wasn't concerned that it would lead
to the זרע zera *zera*. Either that it would lead to arousal
but not to the זרע zera. *zera* or that again even though
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does have an idea of זרע zera *zera*
by women of seed, it's not the concern of זרע לבטלה zera
l'vattala? *zera levatala*. זרע לבטלה zera l'vattala *Zera levatala* was only a
concern of actual ejaculation and male זרע zera. *zera* and so on
and was not a concern by women. So one way of understanding
this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, why it's not a problem by women, is
basically that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is not concerned with the biology
is different, that women don't get as aroused or if they do
get as aroused it certainly doesn't lead to seminal emission and therefore
we're not concerned with female arousal, we're concerned with male arousal. I
will tell you תוספות Tosafos, *Tosafot*'s explanation in a minute and then
we can have a minute or two of reflection on the implications
of all this. Yes, Rachel, you had a question.
Well my question is that in the previous דף *daf* we learned
all about the things that make a man very anxious and unable
to... well
what we learned was that what you're thinking is important to arousal.
Right. And this is done in the context of making sure that
he is not טמא tamei, *tamei*. So why is the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* so worried about him?
Well because he could be טמא *tamei*. I mean why would there
even have been a need for him to check?
No, there's certainly a need.
Right, because... right. So one of the points to point out is
the need for him to check is he might have had seminal
emission and the concern here is... so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
going to discuss that but one way of understanding this, which we'll
get to in a minute... I'm sort of getting ahead of the
next line, but the short answer is that you exacerbate the problem
if you're checking for a man. Right. Because if checking leads to
arousal and leads to seminal emission, such that if you're too busy
checking for seminal emission, it'll lead to greater concerns of seminal emission.
So the whole idea is to try to avoid too much concerns
and here the point is like a little catch-22.
The more you check to avoid, the also more you create the
problem. So that's also a factor here.
People may not know and have...
Right. And we're going to discuss that in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
But at least anyway there are ways of checking without manipulating the
genitals, which is just sort of looking on your clothes and so
on. And if a man thinks it's happened he should check, but
it's talking about כל המרבה *kol hamarbe*, doing more than is strictly
necessary. Yes, Rivka.
I'm concerned with the emphasis on excessive checking for women because there
are other areas of הלכה halachic *halakha* life like כשרות *kashrut*, שבת
*Shabbat*, we don't have to obsess then worry that... doing the violation
then not the—if it just said women should check, fine, but כל
המרבה is בשבח, b'shvach, it's really, like, it's training women to be
constantly obsessed with this
and to be constantly seeing themselves as a source of טומאה.
tumah.
Analogous, right?
Right, that's a very good point.
Where women are constantly told the more you check the better it
is.
Right. No, I mean, I did give you praises of כל המרבה
הרי זה משובח, kol hamarbeh harei zeh meshubach, but it's like in
מצוות עשה mitzvos asei and סיפור יציאת מצרים, sippur yetzias Mitzrayim, right?
It's a very good point, and I mean, it goes back, I
guess, to a point you made before, which is sort of not
just creating a lot of anxiety and high demands, but also particularly
around them as potential sources of טומאה. tumah. And I mean, is
that your point as well? A relation. Let's say, no matter what
it was, just the idea of
having to constantly
be checking, right?
You check it once, once a week, whatever it is. It's not
constant, right? The more you do it, the better it is? No.
Not that I can think of. I mean, it is true that
we have crazy,
super-heightened levels of restrictions around טומאה וטהרה, tumah v'taharah, but not that
it means constant anxiety and constant checking the same way you do
here. So I think that's a point very, yes. I don't have
good answers to your questions.
You're right, it's a very valid point.
Yes. So there is a concern with הוצאת זרע לבטלה hotza'as zera
l'vattala for women? Is there?
Well, I'm going to get back to that. Let me just give
the explanation first and then I'm going to talk. Is there a
concern about—is there a הלכה halakha concern about female masturbation, end of
the day?
Masturbation, but not פליטת זרע? plitas zera?
Well, that's the question. I will talk about that. Let me give
you the תוספות Tosafos explanation, one last point, and then I'm going
to talk about the practical implications of this. Go ahead.
This משנה Mishnah is not saying whether this is at all times
or limited to a time when we have to worry about טומאה.
tumah.
Yeah, but the whole context is טומאה וטהרה. tumah v'taharah. I mean,
עוסק בטהרה. oseik b'taharah. That's how we've contextualized everything. Okay, so. Now,
let me give you תוספות Tosafos explanation. So one explanation has to
do with the
biological reality, and whether we consider that the זרע zera of women
is part of the concern of זרע לבטלה. zera l'vattala The other
explanation is that of תוספות, Tosafos and תוספות Tosafos says women are
not commanded on זרע לבטלה. zera l'vatala Why are they not commanded
on זרע לבטלה? zera l'vatala. Because תוספות Tosafos understands, this is in
the name of רבנו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, that the prohibition of זרע
לבטלה zera l'vatala. is a function of the מצוה mitzvah of פרו
ורבו, pru u'rvu, which as we know in גמרא יבמות, Gemara Yevamos,
although it's debated, and he deals with the other side, is a
מצוה mitzvah on the man, פרו ורבו. pru u'rvu. So he sees
זרע לבטלה zera levatalah. as a sort
of—as a destroying of the semen, something that could have led to
procreation, and emitting it in a non-procreative context, and a non-marital context,
obviously there's a מצוה mitzvah to have sex between husband and wife,
even if the woman is after her childbearing years or is pregnant
or whatever. It's not that all sex only has to have the
procreative context, but certainly not even in a marital context is seen
as a counter, you know, as an undermining, a contradiction to the
mandate of פרו ורבו. pru u'rvu. That's the way תוספות Tosafos sees
it, and therefore women are not in that obligation. And he sees
fundamentally it's not about biology, it's just that they are excluded from
that obligation. Now, how is this relevant? It's actually relevant in two
important ways. Number one, let's deal with the issue תוספות Tosafos deals
with, and then I'll deal with the other issue. The question is,
are women commanded on—to destroy the male seed? So the issue here
is about women using certain forms of birth control, let's say, that
would destroy the male semen in her body. So spermicide is a
question, although תוספות Tosafot didn't deal with that. Nowadays there are some
that say spermicide is not like active destruction, it's passive, it becomes
absorbed in the body, but some raise the issue about spermicides. תוספות
Tosafot raised the question
about a מוך, moch, which is a pad, which I guess the
closest comparison nowadays would be a diaphragm nowadays, which basically would cause
the semen to go out of the body, would undermine the possibility
of
pro—of leading to conception. Is that a responsibility of the woman? Because
it's the woman using it, the man isn't using it. He's not
being משחית זרעו, mashchis zaro, and the woman is being משחית mashchis
the man's זרע. zera If you consider that an act of השחתת
זרע. hashchasas zera. Now, that leads to a broader question, and this
gets to the issue: What is the whole problem with masturbation and
ejaculation? Is it, if it's a problem of, you know, sort of
a פרו ורבו pru u'rvu problem, then it doesn't—it's not so much
as a problem about sexual indulgence and so on, it's more just
the destruction of the seed. So therefore, a woman could actually be
doing השחתת זרע hashchasas zera even if she didn't masturbate. You know,
that's one way of conceptualizing it.
Also if you had already fulfilled the מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו
pru u'rvu then—
Yeah, although it gets broadened. It's not technically you're not being מקיים,
m'kayem, although תוספות asks that and he says, 'Yeah, but there's a
מצוה mitzvah to have more kids.' It's more like it's a conceptual...
idea, you're supposed to be working at having kids and here you
did an act of זרע zera which is seen as sort of,
you know, an anathema to that or a contradiction to that. It's
a little bit more abstract and broader. But anyway it's not so
much about the self-pleasuring aspect as it is about the destruction of
the זרע. zera So would that apply to women? So תוספות says
that when that it would that
it would not and that according to this women could actually use
even could even destroy men's זרע zera and could use a diaphragm
and so on. So that's one נפקא מינא nafka mina by saying
that it's fundamentally women are excluded from this category gets into halakhic
questions about women's using birth control. That's one question. And it also
is very important in conceptualizing the nature of the problem of masturbation,
ejaculation, it is not about self-pleasuring, it is about the type of
counteracting the concept, you know, the potential of of of conception, of
leading to childbirth. The other approach
is so now that's one difference. The other possible difference is the
question about female masturbation. Is there a halakhic problem with female masturbation?
Is it mentioned in the גמרא? Gemara I don't know. Depends on
what you think בנות הרגשה ידענו benot hargasha yadanu means.
So if you know if the whole issue is about destroying זרע
zera so then fundamentally it's not so much a problem for men
or for women. The act of masturbation per se it's more about
the destruction of זרע zera so that would also sort of exclude
women although we will see later as there's going to be a
lot of גמרא אגדתות Gemara aggadotot or whatever that clearly there one
of the concerns here does have to do with the self-pleasuring aspect
of it. But if the גמרא Gemara is sort of making a
claim that women don't get sexually excited through this or they don't
actually have a זרע zera that there's a concern about being משחית
mash'chit even if it has an idea of זרע zera maybe that's
also a way to say they're not included in that prohibition. On
the other hand one on the other hand you could say no,
maybe it means like momentarily there's not a הרגשה but if you're
doing it for the sake of sexual excitement there is a הרגשה
it is a problem. So part of this question has to do
with what is the problem of השחתת זרע? hashchatat zera? Is it
about something related to פרו ורבו? pru u'revu? Is it about the
sort of self-pleasuring? And the other issue has to do with what
the גמרא Gemara thought the biological reality was with women. And I
will tell you and then I will take the question that it's
interesting you know from a halakhic standpoint because you know on the
one hand it gets to a number of areas where הלכה Halacha,
might not might be sort of
more lenient less restrictive but the reason it's less restrictive comes from
you know you know might be based on certain assumptions which might
be seen of as somewhat offensive. So if the reason it's oh
it's not a problem well you know it's not like people don't
ask the שאלה sha'ala this is actually a question that is asked
you know whether a woman you know I've had שאלות sha'alas you
know whether is there any problem with a woman masturbating right? So
oh it's not a problem because the גמרא Gemara doesn't seem to
think that for you you have sexual excitement or something you know.
So it's a little bit you know so you don't have to
say the reason but anyway you know it does raise interesting questions
about getting to a more in a more sort of lenient result
a less restrictive result but through assumptions that could be very sort
of you know dismissive. Often women are off the radar screen. Men
are you know are the ones that whose sexual life we're concerned
about and not women. So that makes it maybe less restrictive for
women but on the other hand because they're being sort of they're
not on the radar screen. Yes Rachel.
Is there really a what I'm just confused I don't understand the
prohibition against משחית זרע mash'chit zera is it because they felt that
זרע zera. was a limited resource or was it a pleasure issue
in which case the the the prohibition
should apply to men and women if they don't get pleasure elsewhere
by yourself?
Right. So that's what I was saying and maybe it was
too embedded in the back and forth so let me pull that
out again and say it again. So certainly one way to understand
it is a pleasure issue we're going to get to that in
the גמרא. Gemara If so and it has nothing to do really
with the זרע zera and it could actually be very problem just
about you know arousal and erection for men and masturbation even if
it doesn't lead to זרע zera and we will see not all
the sources talk about זרע zera some of them just talk about
you know leading you know arousing even without the זרע. zera And
there definitely could be the self-pleasuring issue. If you were to say
that then ask why could it then be different than women? It
would only be if you would explain that the phrase of בנות
הרגשה means we don't think women get aroused that way. We
don't
think that leads to arousal which is again basically being sort of
oblivious to the female reality. No no no the first explanation is
it's not about wasting. It's just about arousal and self-pleasure and that
the idea of sexual pleasure is about a way of connecting individual
a man and woman and you know and and that's what and
that's the sort of the legitimate focus of sexual pleasure and it's
not about just self-pleasure so it's not about the wasting that's not
about the זרע zera at all. To the best of my knowledge,
I do not know that the גמרא Gemara ever makes any claim
or assumption that the זרע zera, is a limited resource. And you're
right, if it's about, oh, you're countermanding פרו ורבו, pru u'rvu, what
do you mean countermanding פרו ורבו? pru u'rvu? It's not like it's
a limited resource, it's not like I'm not going to be able
to do it otherwise. Right, what? Eggs. Yeah, I do understand that.
So anyway, but the point is, and that goes back to the
point before: How do you understand this Rabbeinu Tam's approach about it
being פרו ורבו? pru u'rvu? So I'm saying technically you make פרו
ורבו pru u'rvu more difficult? I don't think so. I think it's
a little bit more abstract. It's like making a claim that, you
know, this type of seed is, semen is seen as supposed to,
the release of semen is supposed to be seen as something that
leads to, or general in a context which could bring about, you
know, conception. And therefore even if a man's wife is not fertile
or whatever, at least it's in that type of an ongoing, you
know, structure and context. But when it's outside of that context, it's
seen as, you know, somewhat, you know, contradictory to the goals of,
you know, to the goals
of פרו ורבו. pru u'rvu. But I don't think it's the narrow
technical point of like somehow this is making it harder to do
the מצוה. mitzvah. Then your question would be, you know, an excellent
one, but I don't see it being phrased exactly that way. I
see it more being phrased as like as like this was something
that under normal contexts should have been in a, you know, under
normal circumstances should have been in a context where פרו ורבו pru
u'rvu was in the framework of things, and it's not, so it's
sort of a statement of a disregard for the concern of, you
know, for the point of for at least one of the whatever
for the for the possibility for the potential of childhood, yes. Dov
had a question. Yeah.
With regards to homosexuality, there seems to be a pending concern, if
not an exclusive one, on male homosexuality as opposed to female. Is
there a connection do you think?
I don't know, I think it's I don't think that's about the
question of semen, because obviously the act of sex is without semen,
but I think it is a does reflect a male bias that
the גמרא Gemara understands that the only definition of a sex act
is penetration, is you know is with the penis penetrating an orifice.
So you can have a man having sex with a woman and
a man having sex with a man because you know with one
of the genital orifices but you cannot have a woman having sex
with a woman. So it does still come from a male perspective
of you know what sex is. So that might also be related
in the sense that a male perspective of sort of the sexual
matter is semen and not you know and sexual excitement is male,
but so it might be part of that same constellation but that's
more specific about the sense that sex is penetration.
Wait a minute, there I
go with two people with hands up first.
Yeah, Doug you did have your hand up. Okay, go ahead Michael.
Go ahead. This one? Okay, go ahead Dov, Dov had a question
last.
So what this actually involves בל תשחית bal tashchit but you know
of a different
sort,
but no no no, let
me let me draw out the analogy. You know we said it
was very hard to do בל תשחית, bal tashchit, you know because
it's not really about, so why can't we say over here this
again this is the גמרא's explanation where they you could quote engaging
in some sort of like מצוה mitzvah right? Because you want to
know if you're טהור tahor or not. So it's not לבטלה l'vatala
because it's for a purpose.
Okay, so I'm not going to use a בל תשחית bal tashchit
analogy, but the question about זרע לבטלה zera levatalah, and what constitutes
לבטלה l'vatala is a very good one because, you know, there it
gets the whole question about can a man masturbate in order to
use the semen for for, you know, for IVF? And what other
constitution what other circumstances would constitute not לבטלה? l'vatala? So those
are all very good. And part of the answer to what you're
saying said is what we're about to see in the next line
is that part is that here you exacerbate the problem. The idea
is to make sure you haven't had semen so you're טהור, tahor,
don't do a check that's going to increase the likelihood. Okay? So
here it is a לבטלה l'vatala concern issue certainly. But your general
point that you have to admit sometimes it's not לבטלה l'vatala and
what constitutes that is a very important practical למעשה l'ma'aseh question about
this issue.
There are different ways you're supposed to check or you just don't
be well
so let's read we will see that in the גמרא. So let's
continue. So that was a fun first few lines, let's continue. Okay,
תנא. tanna. במאי, b'mai, okay, so the גמרא says like this. אי
הכי ei hachi מאי איריא מרבה? mai irya marbe? אפילו לא מרבה
נמי? afilu lo marbe nami? So if it's such an issue for
men, why does it say if you do it a lot? Even
if you do it at all it should be a problem. No,
קתני מרבה. katani marbe. Why did we say if you do it
a lot? And now here it's a funny Aramaic. It's not אנשים,
it's א נשים. a nashim. It's going on the women. Meaning we
say a lot should be praised as for the women. For the
men, even a little is a problem. All right. תנא tanna במה
דברים אמורים, bameh devarim amurim, when is this true that men should
not check? לענין שכבת זרע, l'inyan shichvat zera, when it comes to
the concern of semen. אבל לענין זוב, aval l'inyan zav, when it
comes to a non-seminal flow that makes them טמא, but it's a
penile flow, אף הוא משובח, af hu meshubach, he is praised, אף
הוא משובח כנשים, af hu meshubach k'nashim, even he is praised like
women, because in those circumstances, okay, the checking although you're checking your
genitals and it could lead to excitement it could lead to excitement
and it could lead to semen, but
nevertheless it's you've got to, it's not,
you really have no choice the way the רא"ש *Rosh* says it
here. He says, one case itself contradictory. You're trying to you're concerned
about semen and you're checking in a way that's going to increase
semen. No, you're concerned about זיבה *ziva*. So therefore it is true
that it raises a little bit of a risk of seminal emission
but you still it's not self-contradictory and you have to make sure
that you did not have this flow. Let me just see the
line here in the רא"ש *Rosh*. Hold on. He has something like
that.
One minute. Oh
right, I'm sorry. The רא"ש *Rosh* makes another point. He says that
when men have a seminal emission that usually comes with you know
they know it happened because they you know they feel it in
their body. And therefore there is less of a necessity to check
for it physically you know by
genito-manipulation because there's more of an awareness of whether it happened. So
therefore the need for it is much less. But for זיבה *ziva*
which flows without any sensation in your body, it just flows sort
of you know sort of like naturally but whatever without sensation, so
in those types of cases it's an issue that
you do need to check more. So this gets to Michael's point.
Let me take a step back and mention this right? So not
only are we saying we're concerned about masturbation or זרע לבטלה zera
levatalah. *zera levatala* by men, but we're saying that that concern overrides
concerns that maybe they're טמא *tamei*. And why does it override those
concerns? So as you see in what we just said now it
doesn't always override. If there's a concern about זיבה *ziva* for men,
it doesn't override. So what's the difference? There could be two different
reasons. One is what I said which is almost
it's it's self-contradictory. You're concerned about זרע zera, *zera* so checking in
a way that's going to increase the likelihood of זרע zera, *zera*.
So that's part of why we don't do it because it just
sort of you know it sort of it contradicts itself. The other
and therefore wouldn't be true by זיבה *ziva* wouldn't be self-contradicting. The
other possibility which the רא"ש *Rosh* says is is that there's other
ways of checking. When it comes to זרע zera, *zera* there's other
ways of checking just being sensing whether you had a sensation in
your body and therefore there's no need to do this checking. But
the basic point is that it's not always forbidden. It's forbidden when
it doesn't make sense or when that or when it's not necessary.
Yes.
My sense is that the טומאה *tumah* of זב *zav* is a
more serious level of טומאה *tumah* than a טומאה *tumah* of a
קרי *keri*?
It could be but if it's only a זיבה *ziva* of one
or two days it's only the beginning of the process although you're
right maybe he wouldn't be concerned about the זיבה *ziva* until it
happened twice and then by the second flow it would be more
strict than the קרי *keri*. So it could be. But once you're
making things טמא *tamei* the only difference really you know that is
another possibility. Okay so anyway what we see here is it's not
always forbidden by men this manipulation not actually masturbation but the manipulation
if there are some overriding concerns. So now the גמרא *Gemara* goes
on as follows: ואפילו לשכבת
זרע zera *ve'afilu l'shichvat zera* even when it comes to checking for
semen there's ways of doing it in permissible ways. בא לבדוק בצרור
ובחרס *ba livdok betzror uvacheres* if he wants to check with a
stone or with a piece of pottery so to be sort of
looking but not touching with his hand. בודק *bodek* he can
check. ובמטלית לא *uv'matlit lo* you can't check with some type of
a cloth? That's the implication. והתניא Ve-hatanya, *vehatanya* but we taught in
the ברייתא braita. *baraita* בודק עצמו במטלית ובכל דבר שרוצה *bodek atzmo
bematlit uvechol davar sherotzeh* that the man can check himself with a
cloth or with whatever he wants as long as he's not doing
it directly with his hand. So the גמרא *Gemara* says כדאמר אביי
*k'de'amar Abaye* like אביי *Abaye* says במטלית עבה *bematlit ava* no that
you know you can do it when it's a thick cloth when
it doesn't lead to as much stimulation. הכא נמי Hacha nami, במטלית
עבה *hacha nami bematlit ava* so here too when we said a
man can check
even for זרע zera, *zera* that is okay as long as it
is some thick cloth then it never goes so far to say
משובח *meshubach*. But anyway you do as presumably here there's a counter
you know a counter-balancing concern so you do what's necessary but you
shouldn't do more than what's necessary.
It was just to get it to even be past the level
of
permissibility. Exactly.
Right. Right. Or maybe with these things you should but certainly we
wouldn't say המרבה משובח *hamarbeh meshubach*. Okay. והיכא איתמר דאביי *veheicha itamar
de'Abaye* where was אביי *Abaye* said? Because it says we'll apply what
אביי *Abaye* said elsewhere here that it's okay with a thick cloth.
So where did אביי *Abaye* say this? אהא דתנן *aha detnan* what
we taught in the משנה mishna *Mishnah* coming up later: היה אוכל
בתרומה *haya ochel betrumah* a man is eating תרומה terumah *trumah* והרגיש
שנזדעזעו איבריו *vehirgish shenizdaze'u evarav* and he feels like his limbs are
trembling meaning he feels like he might have ejaculated. Okay? So interesting
that this just happened spontaneously but he feels that that's in the
process of happening. What does he do? אוחז באמתו *ochez be'amato* he
holds on to his penis ובולע *uvole'a* meaning to stop the semen
from coming out from coming out of him. He pushes down on
it to stop to stop himself from ejaculating and he swallows the
תרומה *trumah* in his mouth so that he'll remain טהור *tahor* and
he won't be touching תרומה *trumah* when it finally happens ובולע את
התרומה *uvole'a et hatrumah*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says so that's from
the משנה *Mishnah*. So the גמרא *Gemara* asks on this: אוחז *ochez*?
You hold on? והא *veha* תניא *Tanya*! How's that make things better?
It'll make it worse! רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer? אומר *Rabbi Eliezer omer*:
כל האוחז באמתו *Kol ha'ochez b'amato*, any man who holds on to
his penis ומשתין *U'mashtin* and urinates, כאילו מביא מבול לעולם k'ilu meivi
mabul l'olam, *ki'ilu meivi mabul l'olam*, it's like you bring a flood
to the world. Now why the comparison to the flood? Well, first
of all, there's clearly a sense about liquids that are unwanted. I
imagine that's some of it. But רש"י *Rashi* says that it's also
because of כי שחת כל בשר דרכו על הארץ *ki'shicheit kol basar
darko al ha'aretz*, all flesh corrupted the way on the land, which
is understood by חז"ל *Chazal* about that the even the animals had
interspecies breeding, so it's the sort of ejaculation of semen in the
improper context
and therefore it's associated with a sin that brings about the מבול
*mabul*.
But the תרומה *trumah* is in his mouth already.
It's in his mouth, but it's saying it'll make it worse because
if
you- but I mean, it's not so it's not considered in him.
Oh, that's an interesting point. Why don't we say that it's נגיעה
בית הסתרים *negi'ah beis hastarim* which is not considered נגיעה *negi'ah*.
Yeah, that's a good point. Why? No, no, no, because we normally
say that the touching that causes טומאה *tumah* is from the outside
of the body. The touching from the inner parts of the body
do not cause טומאה *tumah*. But you're still being אוכל תרומה בטומאה
*ochel trumah betumah*. That's the problem. The problem is not that you're
מטמא *metamei* the תרומה *trumah*, the problem is you're being אוכל תרומה
בטומאה *ochel trumah betumah*, but a very good question. So actually the
תרומה *trumah* would be טהור *tahor*, but you would transgress because you're
טמא *tamei* and you're eating תרומה *trumah*. Okay. So anyway the גמרא
*Gemara* says, so look, it'll make it worse! So the גמרא *Gemara*
says, אמר אביי amar Abaye במפץ עבה *amar Abaye b'mapatz ava*. No,
it depends how you're holding, what you're- how you're touching. If you
push it down with a thick cloth, you're going to hopefully help
stop it and not make it- not make it worse. רבא אמר
amar *Rava amar* says, אפילו תימא במפץ רך *afilu teima b'mapatz racha*,
no, even if it were a soft cloth, it would not be
a problem here. Why? כיון דעקר עקר *keivan d'akar akar*. Once the
semen has uprooted, it's uprooted, meaning that the whole concern about stimulating
the genitals is that it will cause, you know, semen to flow.
Here it's at the point it's about to come out anyway, you
can't make it worse. Okay, it says you can only make it
better, so we're not concerned that the holding down here will somehow
exacerbate the problem. So yeah, that's a good point, maybe you don't.
Okay,
but that was just sort of a- you know, sort of in
contrast to אביי *Abaye*. So רבא *Rava*'s saying look, in general it's
a problem, but here the guy's in the process, it's not going
to make it any worse. ואביי *V'Abaye* and אביי *Abaye* would say
back, חיישינן דילמא אתי לאוסופי *chaishinan dilma ati l'oseifi*. No, I'm concerned
that if you do it in a way that's stimulating, that it'll
lead to more semen coming out. So, you know, yes, some is
going to come out anyway, but this will just increase it. ורבא
לא חייש דילמא אתי לאוסופי *V'Rava lo chaish dilma ati l'oseifi* and
רבא *Rava* isn't concerned that that will happen. ולא *V'lo*, is that
really true that he shouldn't be concerned? והתניא Ve-hatanya, *V'hatanya*, we taught
in a ברייתא Beraita: *Baraita*, הלמד זה דומה *halamad zeh domeh*, what
is the act of masturbation like in terms of leading to the
ejaculation? לנותן אצבע בעין *L'noten etzba ba'ayin*, like somebody putting a finger
into an eye. What's the comparison analogy? שכל זמן שאצבע בעין *shekol
zman she'etzba ba'ayin*, as long as the finger remains in the eye,
עין מדמעת וחוזרת ומדמעת *ayin medama'at v'chozeret u'medama'at*. It constant- tears come
out and if you keep it in the eye more tears will
come out. So in
the- so masturbation or a stimulation of the genitals, it's not going
to just, you know, the as- if you keep on doing it,
it will cause more and more semen to come out. So how
come רבא *Rava* isn't concerned that if you try to stop it
but you don't do it in the right way it'll cause more
semen to come out? So the גמרא *Gemara* says, ורבא *v'Rava* what
would רבא *Rava* say back? כל אחמומי והדר אחמומי בשעתא לא שכיח
*Kol achmumei v'hadar achmumei b'sha'ata lo shechi'ach*. He says any heating up
and then going back and heating up more at the same- at
that moment is not- is not common. Which presumably means like the
body's already in the process, so to increase it at that moment
is not going to make a difference. Maybe if you did it,
you know, sort of afterwards or whatever it would happen again, but
for whatever moment at that moment. I hope you're not leaving because
you're offended.
But, all right, you're going to miss the end! You're not going
to find out how it all ends anyway. All right, good luck.
So anyway, רבא *Rava* isn't concerned in this context that that'll make
it any worse. Okay, but other contexts may be.
But this is- this is to urinate, right? It says אוחז באמתו
ומשתין *ochez b'amato u'mashtin*.
Or is it- No, no, no, that's what we show that you
should not be holding on and stimulating even inadvertently the genitals because
of what it'll lead to.
So even if you're- even
if you need to go to the bathroom. Now we're going to
get to that in a minute. Okay, yeah.
This discussion seems to assume that the masturba- that the problem is,
you know, הוצאת זרע לבטלה
zera levatalah *Hotza'at zera l'vatala*?
Yes, the waste of זרע zera *zera*.
Yeah, that is definitely true that as you continue in the גמרא
*Gemara*, meaning there are different- there are different sort of themes going
on, and some people try, I saw one scholar try to sort
of do a sort of, you know, sort of like a- I-
sort of try to analyze it by the historical layers of the
גמרא *Gemara* about how much was the concern the זרע zera. *zera*
and how much was the concern the sort of the sort of
sexual indulgence and self-pleasuring without the זרע zera *zera*. There definitely are
both themes present. But you make a very good point that this
discussion right here about adding to the זרע, zera. you know, certainly
seems very, very זרע-focused. zera And that is overwhelming. You know, when
you hear this discussion in הלכה, halakhah it's almost always a discussion
about זרע לבטלה. zera levatala, Now there are other phrases in the
גמרא, מקשה עצמו לדעת, makshe atzmo l'da'at, somebody that causes himself to,
you know, become hard intentionally. So or other types of things like
that which speak not about the זרע zera per se, but those
are almost always understood and contextualized as because it'll lead to זרע
לבטלה. zera le-vattalah But that is not necessarily true. It is possible
that some of these were, you know, intrinsic concerns about self-pleasuring and
so on and that, but there definitely the זרע zera theme is
the overriding one.
Well, but here he admits the pleasure because especially since it's started
about— I
know, that was— that was— that was those points.
No, but is it even relevant?
No, because even inadvertently it could still lead to this sexual stimulation,
you know, like, it's not clear that the concern is that it
leads to זרע, but in this context about the extra זרע, it's
definitely that concern. Okay, let's go on. גופא. Gufa. אמר רבי אליעזר
אומר. Amar Rabbi Eliezer omer. Now we get to this issue about
the urination. כל האוחז באמה ומשתין, Kol ha'ochez b'amah umashtin, somebody holding
onto his genitals and urinating, כאילו מביא מבול לעולם, it's like brings
a flood to the world. אמרו לו לרבי אליעזר, Amru lo l'Rabbi
Eliezer, והלא נטיפי נטפין על רגליו v'halo nitfei nitfin al raglav ונראה
ככרות שפכה, v'nir'eh k'karut shofcha, if you don't hold on, then you—
the person urinates without— without holding, so then the urine will, you
know, the urine won't— you know, go near him and some of
it will drip on his legs, and then people will see he's
got, you know, these urine stains on his— on his clothes, and
people will think that he's got— that his genitals are deformed or
somehow, and you know, he's כרות שפכה karut shofcha that somehow they're—
they're crushed or deformed and therefore not only will he look embarrassed,
but ונמצא מוציא לעז על בניו שהם ממזרים, v'nimtza motzi la'az al
banav shehem mamzerim, people will say it can't be really his kids.
Look at this, this person's got some problem with his genitals, how
could it be that those are his children? And those— his children
will— will get a reputation of being ממזרים. mamzerim. So how should
he go ahead and do this? He's got bigger concerns here. So
אמר להם, amar lahem, he said back to them, מוטב שיוציא לעז
על בניו שהם ממזרים, mutav sheyotzi la'az al banav shehem mamzerim, better
that he should have a— that there should be a evil report
about his children that they're ממזרים, mamzerim, ואל יעשה עצמו רשע שעה
אחת לפני המקום. v'al ya'aseh atzmo rasha sha'ah achat lifnei HaMakom. And
he should not for even one second be evil in the eyes
of God to have manipulated, you know, to have stimulated himself by
holding onto his genitals, which is pretty amazing, you know, shocking number
one how terrible he thinks this thing is. By the way, it's
not that there is זרע, but presumably שעה אחת sha'ah achat is
that moment of sexual stimulation even without the זרע, but that one
moment, how terrible it is. And number two is he's not bringing
bad reputation on himself, right? He's bringing bad reputation on other people,
בניו שהם ממזרים. banav shehem mamzerim.
And he's— one of the things that I heard is this— this
seems like he's taking his own personal...
Well, that's interesting. תניא אידך. Tanya idach.
He's basically saying that if you have to choose, which this is
a tough one that's constantly...
Not
to make your children ממזרים. mamzerim.
Most women choose not to do that at the expense of their
own personal happiness. Here it's telling men, don't, you know, your fate
in the next world is more important than having your children be
considered ממזרים. mamzerim.
That's— yeah. I mean, it's— yeah. Or all of the shame of...
not but considered ממזרים mamzerim or לעז, la'az,
but yeah, to
have everybody assume your children are ממזרים, mamzerim, which means they'll never
marry other than other ממזרים. mamzerim.
I know. I mean, Rabbi Eliezer's position here, right.
But you be a צדיק. tzadik.
Right. Yeah. It's— I mean, he's in the minority there. Rabbi Eliezer's
position is extreme. But you're right, it's really— but it's— I— you're
right. I mean, I cannot begin to understand it. It's extreme. But
you know, and the point you made yesterday also about how it
gets normalized because the גמרא before took Rabbi Eliezer's position for granted.
You can't be אוחז באמה. ochez b'amah. Now as everybody points out,
it doesn't mean we rule like him to the extreme of this
case about urination and so on, but it certainly means that we
rule like him in other situations. But the fact that it's sort
of— he's part of a— a regular part of that discourse and
the implications of it, you're absolutely correct. So let's read a little
bit further that at least we see the contradictory voice. תניא אידך,
Tanya idach, we taught in another ברייתא. אמר להם רבי אליעזר לחכמים,
Amar lahem Rabbi Eliezer lachachamim, Rabbi Eliezer said to the sages, "No,
I've got a solution to your problem. אפשר יעמוד אדם במקום גבוה,
Efshar ya'amod adam b'makom gavo'ah, so you can urinate from a higher
place so it doesn't splatter back on you, וישתין, v'yashtin, and urinate,
או ישתין בעפר תיחוח, o yashtin b'afar tichuach, or on sort of
like, you know, sort of soft earth so it doesn't— it's not
hard, it doesn't splatter back on you.
ואל יעשה עצמו רשע שעה אחת לפני המקום, V'al ya'aseh atzmo rasha
sha'ah achat lifnei HaMakom, and nevertheless do not make yourself evil in
front of God for even one minute." So the גמרא says, "האי
אמר להו ברישא? Hai amar lehu b'reisha? Which of these two answers
did he say before? אילימא קמייתא אמר להו ברישא? Ilima kamaitha amar
lehu b'reisha? First he said, 'I don't care what— what people think
about your children,' so בתר דאמרו לו איסורא batar d'amru lo issura
after he said that, you know, that it's
forbidden regardless of
the..." forbidden. אלא אמר להו ברישא. ela amar lehu beresha. So no,
rather it's the opposite. First he'd say wait I got a solution.
You make a good point, here's my solution. You know, do it
from a higher place. Then ואמרו ליה ve'amru leh and then they
said back to him, oh that's very nice, but אימא מקום גבוה
ואפשר דלא משכח מאי eima makom gavo'ah ve'efshar dela meshkach mai what
if you don't have those solutions available to you? And then he
said אמר להו, amar lehu, you know what? I really don't care.
מוטב שיוציא לעז על בניו ואל יעשה עצמו רשע שעה אחת לפני
המקום mutav sheyotzi la'az al banav ve'al ya'aseh atzmo rasha sha'ah achas
lifnei hamakom and I'd rather that your children be considered ממזרים mamzerim
rather than you be wicked in front of God for even one
second. דכולי האי למה, dekuli hai lamah, why such an extreme?
מפני שמוציא שכבת זרע לבטלה. mipnei shemotzi shichvas zera levatalah. Now this
is what I said before, notice that this is the גמרא, you
know, sort of explaining, here's the concern זרע לבטלה. zera le-vattalah So
this idea is the concern about the זרע or is the concern
about the sexual stimulation in itself, right, the גמרא sort of frames
everything about the זרע, but it's not so clear that all of
these sources that was the only concern. And as we will see
as we continue, there are going to be both of those themes.
The זרע theme and the theme about the sort of self-sexual self-indulgence.
Who's like רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer What?
We don't rule like him in the case of urination, but we
do rule like as the גמרא is clear about this issue about
manipulating the genitals and whatever even in cases when not necessary. And
that goes back to the משנה about, about, you know,
בנשים שקוצץ. banashim shekotzeitz. So דאמר רבי יוחנן de'amar Rabbi Yochanan and
now we are connecting this statement of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer? which
is a תנא tanna with a statement of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
who is a first generation אמורא Amora and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
is the one that certainly highlights the concern of זרע. דאמר רבי
יוחנן de'amar Rabbi Yochanan כל המוציא שכבת זרע לבטלה kol hamotzi shichvas
zera levatalah anybody that meaning man that you know that ejaculates the
semen for no purpose חייב מיתה chayav misah is deserving of death.
שנאמר shenne'emar וירע בעיני ה' אשר עשה vayeira be'einei Hashem asher asah
this is by, what's his name? אונן. Onan. אונן, Onan, thank you,
where we get the word onanism from. וימת גם אותו vayamas gam
oso and God killed Onan the same way God killed ער. Er.
Now, not only was he habitual I should mention this because this
is a very widespread assumption especially with the word onanism that the
sin of אונן Onan was זרע לבטלה, zera le-vattalah but actually פשט
pshat of the פסוקים pesukim is that the sin of אונן Onan
was what? He would not do יבום yibbum with his wife, with
his brother's wife, thank you, where he was not fulfilling his brotherly
obligation towards his sister-in-law, right? That so the way he wasn't fulfilling
it was that he was משחית ארצה. mashchis artzah. Not that that
was intrinsically the sin deserving of death. Nevertheless, you know the גמרא
takes it and certainly, you know, Christians and, you know, whatever, the
sin of Onan and onanism is the sin of זרע לבטלה. zera
levatala. Yes.
So but it's
in general if it says זרע לבטלה zera levatala has to do
with the anti-פריה ורביה. periyah urviyah.
Right. So that's the way to connect them. But so yes, but
still, you know, here there was a specific mandate with this woman
and it was being countermanded. But yes, you abstract it a little
bit and then it's not such a big difference if the idea
is about wasting the פריה ורביה periyah urviyah opportunity. And that I
think fits in by the way to the idea of חייב מיתה
chayav misah because חייב מיתה chayav misah fits better if you see
it a type of a virtual murder virtual wasting of life and
that is a theme that we are about to see in a
moment. So we will talk a little bit later about the sort
of broader issue about what we do with all these גמרות.
You would say that the wife is נדה niddah at the time
and you wouldn't be able to go in anyway.
All right. Okay fine. So fine I'll let hold off on that.
רבי יצחק ורבי אמי אמרי Rabbi Yitzchak veRabbi Ami amri כאילו שופך
דמים ke'ilu shofech damim and this seems to make exactly that bridge
about the idea of wasting life or potential life. By the way,
the other important point to mention is is that there was an
ancient understanding about the semen that you know the semen was basically
like little men homunculus. Yeah, homunculus. So there actually was not just
sort of wasting
life in the sense of potential life that if this connected with
the whatever, but there actually was like miniature life being destroyed which
might also be why the male semen was considered more problematic wasting
that than the female זרע even again going back the גמרא did
acknowledge the sense of female זרע. All right, so anyway,
where were we? כאילו שופך דמים ke'ilu shofech damim like he committed
murder שנאמר shenne'emar the פסוק pasuk says הנחמים באילים hannechamim ba'eilim those
that warm themselves amongst the terebinths or whatever these trees תחת כל
עץ רענן tachas kol eitz ra'anan under every leafy tree שוחטי הילדים
shochtei hayeladim slaughtering of the children בנחלים bannechalim in the wadies תחת
סעיפי הסלעים tachas se'ifei hassela'im underneath these the cracked rocks. אל תקרי
שוחטי al tikrei shochtei do not read it as slaughter אלא ela
with a sin סוחטי sochtei to squeeze. So you kill the children
by squeezing them out of your body. So that and רש"י also
emphasizes the idea of
warming. So here you really see the idea that it's considered like
a destruction of life in very harsh terms. So this is very
זרע-focused. Now we get something that's much more focused on the self-pleasuring.
רב אסי אמר, Rav Assi amar, כאילו עובד עבודת כוכבים, ke'ilu oved
avodat kochavim, like he worshipped idolatry. כתיב הכא ktiv hacha תחת כל
עץ רענן tachat kol etz ra'anan וכתיב התם u-ktiv hatam על ההרים
הרמים ותחת כל עץ רענן, al he-harim ha-ramim ve-tachat kol etz ra'anan,
it speaks about worshipping idols on all of the high mountains and
under every leafy tree. And the גמרא is going to say and
in general the idea of idolatry, a very common theme and it's
going to be made explicit as we turn the page, is that
once a person gives in to his evil desires, his more lustful
desires and so on, one thing leads to another and basically you
are letting your desires rule you and it could then lead to
idolatry in the sense of basically leads to a life without restrictions
because you basically are giving yourself over to your desires. So that's
the association seems to be with idolatry. So there you go, the
difference about the semen and the pro-sexual life as opposed to the
self-pleasuring is really nicely framed right here.
רב יהודה ושמואל הוו קיימי איגרא. Rav Yehuda ve-Shmuel havu kaimei igra.
So now a little story. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda and שמואל, Shmuel.
you might know רב יהודה Rav Yehuda usually אמר רב יהודה אמר
שמואל, amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, like he was the
תלמיד מובהק talmid muvhak of שמואל. Shmuel רב יהודה Rav Yehuda and
שמואל Shmuel: were on a roof דבי כנישתא דשף ויתיב בנהרדעא, de-vei
knishta de-Shaf ve-Yativ be-Neharde'a, in the synagogue of שף ויתיב Shaf ve-Yativ
in נהרדעא. Neharde'a. שף ויתיב Shaf ve-Yativ is found... ויתיב Yativ means
like it was
laid and settled. So there actually is a story, a version that
they brought some of the stones from the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
when they were sent into
גלות Galut and carried and used them to lay the foundation for
this בית הכנסת. Beit HaKnesset. But anyway whatever it is, it was
called שף ויתיב. Shaf ve-Yativ. This was the בית הכנסת, Beit HaKnesset,
the shul they were on the roof of this synagogue. אמר ליה
רב יהודה לשמואל, Amar lei Rav Yehuda le-Shmuel, so רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda said to שמואל: Shmuel צריך אני להשתין, tzarich ani le-hashtin, I
have to urinate. אמר ליה Amar lei שיננא, shinana, he said to
him "sharp one," which was his way of referring to him,
אחוז באמתך והשתן לחוץ, achoz be-amat'cha ve-hashten la-chutz, go ahead, hold onto
your genitals and go urinate over the roof. So the גמרא says,
היכי עביד הכי, heichi avid hachi, how could he do that? והתניא,
it's amazing that that story was recorded and passed down. והתניא, we
taught in a ברייתא: רבי אליעזר אומר כל האוחז באמתו ומשתין כאילו
מביא מבול לעולם, Rabbi Eliezer omer kol ha-ochez be-amato u-mashtin ke'ilu meivi
mabul le-olam, that you can't and you can't. Now of course it's
interesting why do we פסקן pasken like רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer, But
notice, here
you're on a higher place. Exactly. So even if we don't
rule like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer that's because when there are no
alternatives. But here you are in a higher place, so there were
alternatives, so why did שמואל Shmuel tell him he was allowed? אמר
אביי עשאוהו כבולשת, asauhu ke-boleshet, they made it like the case of
the invading army. What does that mean?
דתנן במתניתין: De-tnan be-matnitin: בולשת שנכנסה לעיר, boleshet she-nichnesa le-ir, an invading
army comes into a city. בשעת שלום, Bi-sh'at shalom, if it's at
a time of peace, they're just encamping in the city, but they're
not in the middle of fighting a battle, so you have to
be concerned that they drank some of the wine and that's יין
נסך. yayin nesech. חביות פתוחות אסורות, Chaviyot petuchot asurot, open barrels are
forbidden, you have to assume that they helped themselves to the wine.
סתומות מותרות, Stumot mutarot, sealed barrels are permissible obviously. בשעת מלחמה, Bi-sh'at
milchama, if they're in the middle of battle, אלו ואלו מותרות, elu
ve-elu mutarot, they don't have time to stop and drink wine and
even the open barrels are permissible. לפי שאין להם פנאי לנסך, Lefi
she-ein lahem pnai le-nasech, they don't have time to do a libation.
Maybe they have time to drink, they're not having time to do
a libation. I don't know, if you're in battle you might stop
and want to make an offering to your God. But anyway,
אלמא, alma, כיון דבעיתי, keivan de-ba'itei, since when people are afraid, לא
אתו למנסך, lo atu le-manasech, they're not going to be able to
focus about other things and spend a minute to do this libation.
הכא נמי,
here too, you're urinating from the top of a roof. כיון דבעיתי,
Keivan de-ba'itei, since you're afraid you might fall over, לא אתו להרהורי,
lo atu le-hirhurei, you're not going to be able to have
use as an opportunity that will lead to sexual stimulation. That's actually
interesting because the גמרא acknowledges that what leads to
sexual stimulation is not just the physical manipulation, but it's also the
mindset at the
time. So if you're at the edge of a roof, even if
you're manipulating your genitals, we don't have to be concerned about the
sexual stimulation.
When רבי אליעזר said after יעמוד אדם במקום גבוה, ya'amod adam be-makom
gavo'ah, he meant another מקום, makom, not a roof?
Yes, a place where it wasn't like you were at the edge
of a roof and you might fall off. Okay, והכא מאי ביעתותא
איכא, ve-hacha mai bi'ituta ika, what fear is there? So I've already
told you: איבעית אימא ביעתותא דליליא ודאיגרא, i-ba'it eima bi'ituta de-leilya ve-de-igra,
it's night and a roof. Who said it was night? But if
it wasn't night, we have to say so what if it's a
roof, you can be careful on a rooftop, they were sitting on
the roof to begin with. But if it was night and a
roof, okay, then you'd be afraid you'd fall over. איבעית
אימא ביעתותא דרביה, i-ba'it eima bi'ituta de-rabbeih, he's afraid that his רביה
rabbeih is right there. That could be a little
distracting. ואיבעית אימא ביעתותא דשכינה, ve-i-ba'it eima bi'ituta de-Shechinah, the divine presence
on the top of a שול, shul, you're not going to start
to have sexual
thoughts. the awe of God. Okay, so that, but the difference is
is that this awe of God here is not just because they
were in a שול, shul, it's actually going to make a statement,
רב יהודה בר רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda bar Rav Yehuda, right, was
generally so פרום frum that he would never that it would never
have been an issue for him.
דקרי שמואל עליה, de-kari Shmuel alei, because שמואל Shmuel said right, exactly,
שמואל Shmuel said about רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, אין זה ילוד אשה,
ein zeh yelud isha, it's like this person isn't even the son
of a woman, he's like he's not even human, he doesn't have
any sexual thoughts. Okay, so I don't want to be that, at
least at least not in any context where it would be inappropriate.
Okay, ואיבעית אימא, ve-iba'it eima, so the next answer is actually נשוי
היה, nasui haya, maybe he was married. And that's interesting because it's
not just somebody like who's a super צדיק tzaddik like רב יהודה,
Rav Yehuda, maybe context does matter. Now that we're just going through
a whole case where context might not matter, okay, maybe context matters.
דאמר רב נחמן, de-amar Rav Nachman, אם היה נשוי מותר, im haya
nasu mutar, if the person was married, it's permissible. Now why why
is that? Does the גמרא think that if a man, yeah, to
hold your genitals while you're urinating. Now why? I don't think it
means that the גמרא felt that if a man was married he
didn't have other sexual desires outside of his marriage or, you know,
when he wasn't having sex with his wife, but at least it
meant that he had a legitimate outlet. And it meant that therefore
we don't have to be concerned that it's like overwhelming his thoughts
all the time and that it's such a heightened concern that even
when it's for a legitimate purpose, we're going to forbid it.
But then again, I mean, let's say he's on a business trip
and away from his wife. I understand.
Or, you know, some men are more highly sexed than other men
and it might not have to do with married or not married,
it might have to do with other factors. That's true, but you
know the גמרא as a legal system has to make at least
some some formal distinctions and it's saying, you know, for some in
some cases, it's a less of a heightened concern. Now that doesn't
mean it's permissible to masturbate and be מוציא זרע לבטלה. mozi zera
levatala. It's talking about manipulating the genitals for a for a legitimate
purpose, and are we concerned about this as an incidental concern? So
it makes this distinction. ואיבעית אימא, ve-iba'it eima, כי הא אורי ליה,
ki ha orei lei, he taught him like the following: דתני אבוה
דרבי סימן בר חייא, de-tani avuha d'Rabbi Siman bar Chiya, אבל מסייע
בביצים מלמטה. aval mesaye'a be-beitzim mi-lemata. You can't manipulate the actual the
shaft, but you can you can sort of lift it up so
it doesn't, you know, so the urine doesn't get on you by
by supporting the scrotum. So that's permissible. Which I don't know, I
would think that that could also be a factor in terms of
masturbation and sexual stimulation. ואיבעית אימא, ve-iba'it eima, כי הא אורי ליה,
ki ha orei lei, the following thing שמואל taught רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda about how to deal with this: דאמר רבי אבהו אמר רבי
יוחנן, de-amar Rabbi Abbahu amar Rabbi Yochanan, גבול יש לו, gvul yesh
lo, there's a limit to where it's a problem. מהעטרה ולמטה מותר,
me-ha'atara u-lemata mutar, from the crown below, below here means towards the
tip, okay, that that is permissible, that actually does not get as
does not lead toward as much sexual stimulation. מהעטרה ולמעלה אסור, me-ha'atara
u-lemala assur, from the crown above, means towards the body, אסור, assur,
that is forbidden. So of course, it's a little bit hard I
would imagine to hold above the crown and to try to urinate,
right, but anyway, that is not as much affected by by manual
manipulation as the rest of the penis.
So it would still be a problem outside of this urination, like,
you know, in the cases of...
Yeah, yeah, yeah, we're not allowing it for the purpose of self-indulgence
and pleasure, and this is all when it's being done for another
purpose.
Okay, no, but even then, you know, we had things like use
a מטלית metlit or whatever it is, those you shouldn't do that,
you know, for checking for תרומה purposes even...
No, no, no, we have a range of things which are make
it allowed when it's not done for purposes of of masturbation and
stimulation, when it's done for other legitimate
purposes. אמר רב, amar Rav, let's try let's get to the משנה
here. המקשה עצמו לדעת יהא בנדוי. ha-mekasheh atzmo lada'at yehei benidui. Somebody
who actually intentionally, and notice here it doesn't speak about זרע לבטלה,
zera levatala. somebody who intentionally makes himself hard, a man intentionally לדעת,
lada'at, should be בנדוי. be-nidui. Now what does it mean יהא בנדוי?
yehei benidui? So תוספות says it doesn't mean that automatically he's בנדוי.
be-nidui. It's advice to the rabbis of the of the of the
period to put him in נדוי. nidui. Of course, how does he
know? I don't know. But anyway, but at least that softens it
a little bit. It doesn't mean that a person who does this
is automatically בנדוי. be-nidui. So the גמרא says יהא בנ... ולימא אסור,
yehei be-ni... u-leima assur, why just why not just say it's אסור?
assur? Why do you have to go so far to say he
should be בנדוי? be-nidui? So it says, no, this is worse than
normal things. No kidding, you got that idea before. דקא מגרי יצר
הרע אנפשיה, de-ka magrei yetzer hara a-nafshei, you are actually inciting the
יצר הרע yetzer hara against yourself. You're, you know, you're not just
sinning and indulging in your desires, it actually, you know, you are
stimulating yourself and increasing your your your your your your lust. ורבי
אמי אמר, ve-Rabbi Ammi amar, רבי אמי Rabbi Ammi says, נקרא עבריין,
nikra avaryan, you're called a sinner, which is a little not as
bad as I assume יהא בנדוי. yehei benidui. שכך הוא אומנתו של
יצר הרע, she-kach hu omanuto shel yetzer hara, now we get to
elaborate, he even goes specifically on רבי אמי Rabbi Ammi or whatever,
but we go to elaborate the idea about the about the sort
of giving in to your to your desires, indulging in and and
increasing your own, you know, your lust, this is the way of
the evil
inclination. Today it says give in on this little point ולמחר אומר
לו עשה כך u-lemachar omer lo aseh kach tomorrow it gets you
to concede another action that you shouldn't be doing and everyday you
give a little bit more in to your more base desires ולמחר
אומר לו לך ועבוד עבודה זרה והולך ועובד u-lemachar omer lo lech
va-avod avodah zarah ve-holech ve-oved and so finally it leads to idol
worship. But that quote actually is from an earlier גמרא about עבודה
זרה avodah zarah which the עבודה זרה avodah zarah framing as opposed
to the by the way you notice this is already about sexual
sin and now we've added like murder and it's like עבודה זרה.
avodah zarah. Right. So we've now got all the three cardinal sins
here. But nevertheless the עבודה זרה avodah zarah framing seems to be
this
idea of once you give in to your baser desires it'll lead
to a complete פריקת עול prikas ol like giving up of the
yoke of your restrictions and the מצוות. mitzvot. Okay. דאמר רב אמי
ואמרי לה אמר רב
אמי De-amar Rav Ammi ve-amri lah amar Rav Ammi others say Rav
Ammi says
כל המביא עצמו לידי
הרהור kol ha-mevi atzmo lidei hirhur anybody that brings himself to sexual
thought. Now this is a slightly different than the other things. We've
mentioned זרע we've
mentioned self-indulgence as a problem in itself. Giving in to your
baser desires etc. etc. But here the problem is about sexual thought.
Now you could say that's a problem because it leads to זרע
לבטלה zera levatala, but it's also possible that the גמרא had a
problem about sexual thought in itself. The רמב"ם Rambam in מורה נבוכים
Moreh Nevukhim in particular was very focused on the intellectual life as
the primary spiritual life of a person really spoke about the problem
about sexual thought as taking your mind away from your most
important part of your self is your mind and directing
it towards towards baser issues rather than towards more spiritual issues. And
obviously we know all you have to do is look around and
see all of the sex scandals that people get into and how
it destroys lives of people who might otherwise rationally have made other
choices about how these type a person that's sexually obsessed with thought
what it can do
to the destructive ability of those thoughts which has nothing to do
with the זרע per se. It's just about that type of obsession.
So you're saying someone obsessed or someone just has a random thought?
Well a random thought is maybe a part of it. You're right.
Obsession is taking it to another level. כל המביא עצמו לידי הרהור
kol ha-mevi atzmo lidei hirhur anybody brings himself to intentionally having these
sexual thoughts אין מכניסים אותו במחיצתו של הקדוש ברוך הוא ein machnisim
oto bi-mechitzato shel Ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu does not get into to be
in God's inner circle up in heaven. כתיב הכא ktiv hacha it
says here וירע בעיני ה' vayeira be-einei Hashem again by אונן Onan
it was evil in the eyes of God. וכתיב התם u-ktiv hatam
it says over there כי לא אל חפץ רשע אתה ki lo
El chafetz rasha attah you are not a God that desires
evil לא יגורך רע lo yegurcha ra will not dwell with you.
וירע vayeira so you don't get into the inner circle of God.
That's really harsh. I mean like who doesn't I
don't know that I think is less harsh than the other stuff.
No if you don't have to be seeding.
No no no one has a chance. Right.
I mean well no intentionally. No it doesn't mean if you have
the thought. מביא עצמו mevi atzmo that's
intentionally. Okay. ואמר רבי אלעזר ve-amar Rabbi Eleazar מאי דכתיב mai de-ktiv
what's meant by the verse ידיכם דמים מלאו yedeichem damim maleu going
back to the earlier theme your hands are filled with blood by
ישעיהו Yeshayahu אלו המנאפים ביד. eilu ha-mena'afim ba-yad.
That's an interesting phrase. Those are these these are those that commit
adultery with the hand. So obviously דמים מלאו damim maleu blood is
this idea of wasting of the
seed wasting of life that's the דמים damim but the phrase of
מנאף ביד mena'ef ba-yad meaning adultery with the hand points to another
point. Now not that it's not a man's wife because obviously in
a polygamous society the גמרא was not con... a man could have
sex with a woman who wasn't his wife as long as she
wasn't a married woman. But it is still about the idea about
sex being about being between people and not having sex with yourself
essentially is what it is saying. So that is a type of
adultery in the sense that it is sex with yourself and not
sex with another person. By the way רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe
Feinstein makes a very big deal about this more than some other
פוסקים poskim getting back to the זרע לבטלה zera levatala question about
can a man masturbate in order to produce semen in order
to impregnate his wife for the purpose of IVF. And רב משה
פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein has a big problem with this because he
says there's not just a problem of זרע לבטלה zera levatala. there's
also a problem of מנאף ביד mena'ef ba-yad of how it is
procured and the act of doing it even if it's not for
a לבטלה le-vattalah purpose is considered this act of מנאף ביד. mena'ef
ba-yad. Now that is somewhat unique to רב משה פיינשטיין. Rav Moshe
Feinstein. Try to do it by you can sort of try to
stimulate yourself but without actually manual manipulation. How successful that can be
is a big question. So it's a real
issue for פועה Puah and other places that do הלכה try to
do it under halakhic
authority and try to do it with רב משה Rav Moshe's guidelines.
It makes it very very difficult based on emphasizing this theme of
מנאף ביד. mena'ef ba-yad. תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל tanna de-vei Rabbi Yishmael
לא תנאף lo tinaf you shall not commit adultery לא תהא בך
ניאוף lo tehei becha ni'uf
there should be no aspect of adultery בין ביד
בין ברגל bein ba-yad bein ba-regel even meaning sex with done by
yourself with your... hand, with your foot, any way you stimulate yourself,
that is an act of sex, a type of an adultery. תנו
רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, הגברים, hagvarim, now this is so, okay, we're end
this already, over time, so... but go, go ahead. All right, I
gotta get to the... הגברים והמשחקים בתינוקות. hagvarim vehamisachakim betinokot. This is
going to be more explosive than what we said until now. Converts
and those that that play, which is in quote marks, you know,
sexual play with children, מעכבין את המשיח, meakvin et hamashiach, cause the
Mashiah to be to be held back. בשלמא גרים, bishlama geirim, I
understand what the Gemara's saying, converts. Oh my god, בפסימיות bepessimiut on
Shavuot? כרבי חלבו, keRabbi Chelbo, that's following the approach of Rabbi Chelbo.
דאמר רבי חלבו, deamar Rabbi Chelbo, קשים גרים לישראל כספחת. kashim geirim
leYisrael kesapachat. Converts are bad to Israel as a scab. So they
pull down the people, at least this is one attitude towards geirim
as I'm confident sure there are many different attitudes in the Gemara,
but this is one very negative attitude and therefore that that's not
a good thing. אלא משחקים בתינוקות מאי היא? ela misachakim betinokot mai
hi? What does that mean, you know, understanding it means sexual play
here? אילימא משכב זכור, ilima mishkav zachar, people that have sex with
young boys, men that have sex with young boys? So A, there's
child abuse, but that's not what the Gemara's going to focus on.
בני סקילה נינהו, benei sekila ninhu, so that's an act of homosexuality,
that's deserving of stoning. אלא דרך אברים. ela derech evarim. So maybe
it means they have sex with young boys not actually in something
that is technically an act of sex, but it is through דרך
אברים, derech evarim, which means oral or with hands and so on.
So it's so that's the issue. So so that's true, nevertheless, even
if it's not actual, again the Gemara completely is ignores any concerns
here about, you know, child abuse, and says: אבל בני מבול נינהו.
aval benei mabul ninhu. It's at least זרע לבטלה. Okay, so it's
now it's so therefore it's deserving of the flood, which presumably is
I guess worse than holding back the Mashiah. I don't know, one
is for you, the other is for the entire people, but you
know, for the entire world. But nevertheless, the Gemara says that should
have been phrased differently.
Let's say the flood is definitely worse than not having the Mashiah.
בני דור המבול benei dor hamabul deserving of a flood as opposed
to the Mashiah that's held back for all the world. Well, you
think בני מבול benei mabul means it brings a flood to the
world? I I just understood it as a... אלא, ela, so it's
going to explain תינוקות tinokot not meaning young boys, which is what
it saw before, but it's going to focus on the feminine. אלא
דנסיבי קטנות. ela denasivi katanot. They marry young girls. Okay. So people
who before were upset, you know, by the Gemara, I'm regularly upset
by the fact that the Gemara deals with marriage to underage girls.
Here it says it's a problem. But again, why is it a
problem? Not because again of child what we would consider child abuse
and having sex with underage kids, but דלאו בנות אולודי נינהו. delav
benot olodei ninhu. Because since they are not yet of the age
to conceive, then it's a type of a זרע לבטלה almost. אמר
now, well, not exactly. The Gemara doesn't frame it as זרע לבטלה.
That should be clear that with all the discussions of זרע לבטלה,
nobody says that in the context of at in a marital context.
If a woman is postmenopausal, pregnant, there's still a mitzvah of עונה,
onah, of having regular marital sex, and nobody says that זרע לבטלה
means that every act of sex has to lead to the potential
of procreation. And the Gemara even here when it's talking about underage
girls does not say זרע לבטלה. What does it say? דאמר רבי
יוסי, deamar Rabbi Yossi, אין בן דוד בא עד שיכלו כל הנשמות
שבגוף. ein Ben David ba ad sheyichlu kol haneshamot shebaguf. The Mashiah
won't come, and this is why it ties into Mashiah, until all
the souls are used up. גוף guf here does not mean literally
body. It's understood to be a warehouse of souls. All the souls
that have to get to this world have to be created before
Mashiah can come. So here you could have married a woman that
could have conceived, and you could have been busy having kids and
therefore bringing the Mashiah about. And instead, Mashiah is not coming about
because you're not having kids. שנאמר, sheneemar, כי רוח מלפני יעטוף ונשמות
אני עשיתי. ki ruach milfanai yaatof uneshamot ani asiti. The wind or
the spirit's come are being held back because of the souls that
I have created. So therefore you are not having as many kids
as you could be having and that is holding back the Mashiah.